if you're trying to become a successful
Trader or you're already consistently
profitable but you know you could do
better what we're going to go through in
this video is the most important thing
and yes I know that's a really bold
claim to make and I'm going to have to
back it up throughout this video now but
don't worry it's not going to be
anything like a super secret strategy
I've discovered or a quick hack to
improve your success rate or any of that
sort of bollocks that you see on Tik Tok
instead this is going to be something
that's really practical logical and it's
right at the heart of trading or at
least it should be at the part of good
trading but unfortunately it seems like
well over 99% of Traders neglect this
area either cuz they're overlooking it
they don't realize maybe or they just
don't care about it but this is
something that if you understand it and
you implement it it will improve your
trading doesn't matter what approach or
method you're using what system or
strategy whether you're a complete
beginner or you've been trading for
years this is something you need to
understand and it will improve your
trading so just like the last video this
isn't going to be scripted but luckily
it seems from the comment section of the
last video that most of you prefer this
format which is great news for me
because I hate scripting videos and it
means I can give you so much more detail
and value throughout the video now but
we are going to have some structure so
I'm going to share my screen but before
you click away thinking bloody hell all
this guy bangs on about his
probabilities all the time stick around
because what we're going to go through
is so much more than what we've covered
so far and by the end of this video
you'll understand that you're already
estimating probabilities of your trades
so I'm not asking you to do something
that you're not already doing you
understand why it's important to
explicitly estimate your probabilities
and to track them not just doing it in
your head without realizing it which is
what you're currently doing most likely
you'll understand how to estimate the
probabilities of your trades we've had
this question on loads of our videos
recently the ones about probabilities
people asking okay how do you actually
do it and I did show you in a video
about range trading that hardly anyone
watched you know people ask for videos
going through trades and they not never
watch them and that's going back years
but you that's a whole topic and then
finally we'll go through how to improve
your ability to estimate probabilities
now those of you who have been around
this channel for a while and especially
our members will know that I'm not
really the sort of person that just
throws out an unfounded opinion about
something usually things are well
researched they're based on extensive
testing or a lot of experience and this
is the case here like I'm coming with
receipts because a lot of people have
been disagreeing with me on
probabilities and those people are wrong
and once you understand it properly then
well I'm said this like a few times
already I'm say say it a million times
more it will improve your trading
surprise surprise so grab your tea or
coffee and keep it Arms Reach because uh
in one of my last live stream trading
sessions I knocked over a full cup of
coffee oh [__] so let's get into it now
there's this common phrase that I've
talked about before that trading is a
game of probabilities you've probably
heard this on just about every trading
Channel social media account most
Traders come out with this usually there
a reason to justify their losses like
it's okay we're not expecting a 100%
success rate you know trading is a game
of probabilities or you know when some
indicator or tool or pattern they're
using is not performing they'll say well
it's not meant to work 100% of the time
trading is a game of probabilities now I
agree with that statement I think that
trading is about probabilities I
wouldn't necessarily say it's a game but
we're going to refer to it as a game
throughout this but the problem is most
people who make that statement and I've
said this before their actions don't
align with that
because if trading is about
probabilities then why aren't
probabilities featured in most people's
analysis but there's another problem as
well and that problem is that I think a
lot of people don't actually understand
the role of probabilities in their
trading and much worse than that is I
don't think many trading education
channels understand about the role of
probabilities and I've seen this many
times because there are so many videos
coming out about probabilities in
trading but they all seem to get it
wrong and there's one in particular like
in this industry people
look around for videos that they think
is an interesting topic then they'll
steal all the information repackage it
with a better thumbnail and title and it
will perform well for them now that's
happened to us on many occasions where
we bring out information that's based on
our research uh that's based on you know
our testing our experience whatever and
people will rip it off repackage it and
it will do much better for them than us
because we don't know what we're doing
with the titles and thumbnails and stuff
um but there was one guy and he's been
doing this for years he's a bigger
Channel than us now but he's been
ripping off our content for a long time
and he took our free training and a
couple of the probabilities videos we
did used all the talking points
throughout his video but then when he
came to the conclusion where he was
wrapping things up then he made a
statement that proved that he didn't
actually understand what he was talking
about because he said because of all
these things we've discussed therefore
you should trade with asymmetric risk
reward ratios because that way you can
be wrong more times than your right and
still make a profit now that's right but
it's not really anything to do with
probabilities and so I thought if we go
through this video go through it in as
like simple easy to understand way as
possible and make it clear why it's
important and what role it needs to play
Then when someone inevitably steals or
rips off some of this information or
repackages it then at least they'll get
it right this time it's a bit cynical of
me isn't it oh well so this is what it's
all based around here now this is what
something I spoke about in the last
video as well but I think this really
Paints the picture nicely so let's say
that we're playing a coin TOS game and
when it lands on
heads you're going to give me one pound
okay so that's a minus1 for you and when
it lands on Tails I'm going to give
You2 okay and let's say that we've run
all of these scientific experiments on
the coin to make sure it's fairly
weighted that you don't have to have any
doubts about whether it's going to land
just on heads or tails because at school
when I was a kid I I used to love magic
stuff and I had this 50p that was
weighted so it would always land on
heads and I'd make bets in the
playground and and get money off people
I remember in a French class I did it
with this guy I'm not going to say I was
about to say his name but uh this Korean
guy and he got so angry he punched me in
the head and that was the end of the 50p
game although I have to say he had
pillow fist it wasn't too bad but anyway
let's say that this is the game we're
playing and let's say that it lands on
heads 10 times in a row so you're down
101 okay so put it over here you can
think of that your draw down so on the
11th go do you think that you'll have
any issue continuing with the game do
you think you'll have any problem saying
no let's flip again no you would
continue because you know you've got a
good edge here so there's not really any
situation where as long as you
understand that it is fairly weighted
and there's no advantage on the actual
coin itself there's no reason that
you're not going to to continue playing
as long as you have enough money to
endure reasonable draw down then you'll
keep playing until the opponent or me in
this case is bankrupt and you've got as
much money out of the situation as you
can and you won't have trading
psychology issues you won't try and
change your strategy or your approach
you just keep flipping the coin flipping
the coin flipping the coin letting that
edge play out over time so that means
for this scenario to be like one that
you're comfortable with that you'll keep
playing it has to be that
you know you have an
edge okay so you I know you have an edge
in this case I'm going to say it once
and once only sorry about my handwriting
I know that is terrible and the second
thing is that you need to have evidence
off the
edge
oops okay because if you have evidence
of the edge well if you have evidence
meaning that you have data showing how
this plays out over time but you don't
have an edge well then you're not going
to want to trade it because you know
that if you keep playing that you're
going to lose money like for example if
we knew this was the other way around
you wouldn't want to play anymore so if
you've got evidence and it's showing
that you don't have an edge you're not
going to want to play but if you know
that you have an edge or you think you
have an edge but you've got no evidence
of it then again you're not going to
know whether to play or not because as
soon as you start hitting a losing
streak like when you were down 10 pounds
when you had that draw down you're not
going to know whether that is a sign
that you're actually not you don't have
an edge you're not as skillful as you
thought you were and that you should
stop playing so you need two things to
really feel in control and to keep
playing the game you need to know you
have an edge and you need to have
evidence of that edge so imagine that in
trading if you know you have an edge and
you've got evidence of that edge then
most problems disappear and that's
something we come on to in a second but
let's think about this in trading terms
then so this is if it's a coin but I
want us to think about if it's with
trading and you're going to see why I
believe that the skill of estimating
probabilities is the Holy Grail of
trading because this calculation you see
here is the expectancy calculation so
you have the positive outcome multiplied
by the probability of the positive
outcome minus the negative outcome
multiplied by the probability of the
negative outcome so assuming you like
that you could just pick out some
positive outcomes and negative outcomes
then the real skill here is estimating
the probability not picking out the
outcomes but being able to estimate the
probabilities of them and the more
accurate you are at achieving that
estimating the probabilities the more
you're going to be able to develop an
edge develop an edge and be able to have
the evidence that you have an edge now
imagine this if you are good at
estimating probabilities okay so you not
only that you've developed the skill to
do it but you've now tracked through
your data and proven that you're
accurate with it just imagine what that
would mean for your trading you wouldn't
need necessarily a system or a strategy
at least not one that's telling you when
these criteria met enter a trade like a
pattern or something like that you
wouldn't need to limit yourself to
certain markets or time frames or
activity types or Cycles or anything it
would be the case that any Market any
asset it doesn't matter any Market in
any situation as long as you can Define
the outcomes and you can estimate the
probabilities of them you can determine
if there's an opportunity or not why
because you just take all the
information that you gather plug it into
this calculation and look at the
expectancy if it's positive you can take
the trade if it's negative you don't
take the trade it makes a lot of aspects
of people's trading completely redundant
if you could just master that skill you
know a lot of people spend their time
working on this skill of pattern
recognition they're looking for zones
and fair value gaps and chart patterns
and all these kinds of things and
getting better at spotting these things
and thinking that's improving their
ability to to trade profitably but
instead the real skill that everyone
should be working on is your ability to
estimate probabilities more accurately
because if you can do that you don't
need to have these special strategies
and stuff like that
okay
so think about
it all of these problems that people
encounter will be solved as a result of
improving your probability estimates or
actually just doing it in the first
place so the first thing is that
improves your skill luck balance so this
is something that people don't really
think about that much but we've talked
about in this channel before if you
imagine this Continuum between skill and
luck and we can think of all activities
all sports and and everything being
somewhere on this Continuum so if we
think about like chess chess at the
highest levels I mean if I'm playing
chess against someone probably a lot of
is going to be luck but let's say that
you enter the World
Championships not much of it is down to
luck you're you're mostly here right
chess is going to be somewhere along
here whereas if you're playing roulette
and you're you're not doing like the uh
you know the the secret camera that's
recording the spin of the wheel so you
know what's bet on but you're just like
a normal person then that's all the way
down here at luck there's there's no
element of skill to it then you can
think of things like um poker for
example poker is a mix of luck and skill
because it depends on what cards are
drawn but also there is a skill aspect
to it so I don't know like you could say
maybe it's somewhere like in the middle
or like somewhere along here and so on
now what you'll find is that with many
activities it can be either more luck or
more skill depending on how you approach
it and how good you are at it so let's
think about basketball for example if
you're taking a free throw and you've
never played basketball before how much
of it a skill probably not much but if
you're looking at um you know I don't
know LeBron James I can't think for
better Steph Curry we'll go with Steph
Curry um if you're looking at him taking
free throws how much for his skill and
how much for his luck yeah it's much
more on a skill side but there'll be
elements of the game for the
professionals that will be luck like for
example when it bounces awkwardly off
the rim and someone gets the rebound or
like that wouldn't have got it otherwise
or your know opponent slips over
whatever there's there's elements of
luck there but a lot of it do of skill
so it should be the case that if two
teams playing against each other and
both are fully motivated both are fully
fit and switched on then the more
skillful team is going to to win I mean
you can consider like plays and tactics
and things but anyway so it's kind of
the case for trading that you know
beginner Traders can be all the way down
here like as if they're playing roulette
luck and a really good Trader who is um
doing all the right things maybe is over
here there's still some things that
you're not going to be able to
completely remove because we can also
think of skill and luck as being things
that you can control or things that you
can't control
or it can also
be
uh things that you have some sort of
certainty over and things that you have
complete uncertainty with you know there
there's different ways that we can think
of this like it doesn't matter how
skillful you are you can't control the
markets so there's always going to be an
element where it's kind of out of your
control and it's like okay whatever
happens next happens like you know who
could have imagined that the pandemic
would have struck when it did and the
markets would have uh Gone completely
mad like they did do
so the problem is a lot of Traders
without realizing it are going to be
down here on the luck side but they'll
be doing all their analysis they'll have
a strategy and a system and they will
truly believe that what they're doing is
skill but it's not it's kind of like you
know trying to play a a game of football
and following basketball rules you know
you might be really skilled at
basketball if you play the wrong game
then you're not going to be very
skillful at all you're relying on lug so
it's same kind of thing like most of of
the analysis approaches people use are
just analyzing meaningless things that
it's the clustering illusion it's false
causality um so this whole approach of
estimating probabilities what it does is
it first of all helps you to see where
on this Continuum you are and for some
people it's going to be a really bitter
pill to swallow to realize after years
and years you're actually down here luck
um but wherever you are you can move
yourself more this way to an extent
you'll never be fully on this side but
you can move yourself more this way as a
result of what we're going to go through
in this video it stops you unnecessarily
losing money because going back to the
expectancy calculation you'll be able to
figure out when the situation is
negative expectancy and therefore you
don't take that trade cuz right now many
of you watching this most traders in the
world are taking trades that have a
negative expectancy meaning over time
they'll be losing money on their trades
they shouldn't be taking the trades you
just really quickly I've mentioned this
in videos before so I'll cover this
briefly but your role as a tra TR is not
to try and pick out profitable trades
when you're analyzing a situation you
shouldn't be thinking to yourself will
this trade end up in a profit because
guess what you don't [__] know this
the whole thing of there are things that
are out of your control and things that
are in your control all you can do is
estimate the probability of it being a
profit okay you can't say this is going
to be a profit you never know of 100%
certainty so what Pro probability is it
is it 98% 60 50 40 and the thing is that
and this is something people talk about
all the time they'll say so and so
Trader like some big name Trader uh was
only right 20% of the time and they
still made a profit overall and this is
why you need asymmetric risk returns
that's all nonsense right it's not to do
of the asymmetric risk returns or not is
to do with the probabilities so you
could have um a situation where you have
asymmetric risk returns and the
probabilities are against you so you're
expecting with that particular trade
you're going to lose so for example
let's say you have uh one to two trade
where this is the risk this is the
return but the probabilities of this
compared to this this one actually is
40% and this is 60% now I'm not going to
do the calculation but you can run it
through the calculation before in fact
it's easy anyway so it's let's just do
it okay so you got 2 *
0.4 minus uh 1 * 0.6 so we could say
that's going to be 0.6 that's going to
be
0.8 that minus that equals 0.2 okay
probably watch this back be like hold on
that calculation was massively wrong and
I'll think how could I have got a
calculation that simple so massively
wrong but anyway um what you'll start
realizing is that you're not trying to
pick out a trade that you think will end
in profit you're trying to pick out the
positive expectancy trades because this
one you've got a 60% chance of losing
which means you're expecting when you
open that trade that you're going to
lose and yet it's a trade that over the
long run is going to make you money so
stops you unnecessarily losing money by
taking negative expectancy trades not by
avoiding losing trades it improves your
decision making um because not only is
it going to be about when you enter a
trade but also other actions that you
take scaling in scaling out moving a
stop loss and so on it should all be
based around the probabilities it makes
it easier to improve your trading so you
can identify the areas where you're
trading is weaker we've talked about in
the one of the last videos but we're
going to go through it again and it
solves major trading psychology problems
think about it when I said before about
the the coin TOS game if that was the
situation with your trading you wouldn't
feel fomo and all this sort of stuff you
just keep playing the game keep going
keep going you wouldn't hesitate when
you're entering the trade because you
know if it's positive expectancy that
that's going to make you money over the
long run so all you want to do is keep
trading the right way keep trading keep
trading keep trading keep refining your
probability estimates so you can figure
out where you're getting things wrong
and whereever where it's a negative
expectancy situation and just you know
that becomes the focus of your trading
and not all these issues that hold you
all back right now things that we
discussed in the last video so again I
go back to the skill of estimating
probabilities is the Holy Grail in
trading and I would like to know if
there's something that's more important
than there because I don't think there
is people say all you need is to keep
trading simple and you just need good
risk management and good uh trading
psychology but the thing is if you get
the skill of estimating probabilities
and you get accurate at it well trading
psychology go is out the window it's
gone bye-bye it disappears and the risk
management is all solved for you because
you base it on the probabilities and the
expectancy all right once again who am I
ranting at I don't know I just these
things bother me so here on screen you
can see a lot of the common complaints
or uh you know push back that people
have about this like I shouldn't
estimate probabilities because it's not
possible to estimate probabilities or
you just be guessing it's unnecessarily
complicated you can only rely on success
pH all of this stuff we're going to be
addressing you see when people say it's
not possible to estimate probabilities
I'm going to show you that one you're
already doing it and two it is possible
when it's You' just be guessing yeah to
start with it's more like a guess but
you can improve it's a skill that's
developed but if you're already doing it
and you're relying on that you're
already guessing but you don't realize
it unnecessarily complicated or
difficult you know this is the thing
about trading you don't do things for
the sake of it like we don't do things
that are difficult or complicated
because you know oh it's fun to
challenge ourselves we do it because
that's what's going to improve you if
you think about sports I think about
football a
lot a lot just in general but when I
think about football I think about like
you know you got someone like Cristiano
Ronaldo and you've got someone like I
don't know uh Kieran Richardson both
players that have some Talent one that
didn't give a [__] one that is willing
to do every extra little thing they
could to gain any extra ad I can't talk
any extra advantage
and you look at the trajectory of their
careers and how they're so vastly
different and one of them would be like
it's fine I'm skillful I don't need to
train that hard and the other would be
like I'm going to figure out every final
little Edge that I can get and there's a
quote from Arson Wenger who is a legend
and I won't hear otherwise who said that
the the sort of the big difference
between any talented players was how
hard they trained and what they focused
on in trading that dictated the
trajectory of their careers and not
their initial talent and uh it's the
same in trading like
it's not a surprise to me that 95% of
the market fails because people are not
willing to do the complicated or
difficult things they just want to do
what's simple you see how many of the
videos online that get millions of views
are like simple approach to trading well
if you're looking for simple I mean if
it was possible to just have things
simple and that's all you needed and
well here's first of all if it was
possible to just keep things simple and
to succeed more people would be doing so
then people's argument would be well no
because you need good trading psychology
and that tough to master and good risk
management and blah blah blah well if
you have a simple approach and you can
back test and prove to yourself like you
have the evidence that that's giving you
an edge this really simple approach it's
just like the coin TOS game all of the
tradeing psychology goes out the window
but the fact is either with a simple
approach you don't have an edge or you
don't have evidence of the edge so
anyway uh you can only rely on success
rates will cover why that's not the case
and you won't know if you're correct
will cover why that's not the case I
mean you won't know you're correct on
each individual trade because obviously
if you're estimating a probability well
you only have one outcome so I can't say
Something's Got a 60% chance of
happening then it happens and I say oh I
was wrong because it happened 100% you
know it's we have to take a group of
data and find the average of it or
people just say I'll just stick with
this that I'm doing I'll just stick with
focusing on risk management like you
know people in this industry are so
reluctant to take on new information
that conflicts with what they've already
um like learned and spent a lot of time
invest in like invest in time and effort
into learning if you really want to get
good at this there's that quote by uh
Paul Tuda Jones that you need to what is
it have a indefatigable thirst for
knowledge or something he says like
that's what you really need like to this
day I love learning new things about
trading and you might think oh the fact
you've gone on about probabilities like
so much recently is because you've just
learned about it and no it's not the
case like we have videos from seven or
eight years ago where I was talking
about probabilities calibration all of
that but what I realized in more recent
years as you dig into the research in
various different areas that affect
Traders and when you work with Traders
which I do you know helped hundreds if
not thousands of Traders now and worked
with some really experienced Traders you
start to notice that hold on almost
every problem that people encounter
almost everything that holds back
someone from actually succeeding at this
would be solved by probabilities and so
that's why it's been elevated over time
like to being like the holy grail for me
and that's why I'm focusing on it so
much more now because I'm not sure if
I'll do videos on YouTube beyond the end
of this year and if I don't I want to
make sure that I leave this industry
with everyone understanding and
appreciating probabilities and if I came
back to YouTube 5 years later and saw
everyone obsessed with like measuring
their probabilities and calibrating and
getting better at it I'd be like thank
God and if that was the case and
everyone was learning that and actually
putting the effort into that you'd see
the percentage of losing accounts of
Brokers would drop significantly there'd
be a such a bigger percentage of traders
that are actually succeeding now with
all of those points that we've just been
through the really important thing that
I want you to take on board here is that
you are already doing it this isn't
something new it's just taking something
you're already doing and making it so
much better so you can rely on it and
you're doing it in your everyday life
and you're doing it in your trading so
let's think about in your everyday life
this chart is one of the most depressing
charts you'll ever see in your life you
might not be able to guess what it is
from what's over here this is number of
days each year in the UK that it rains
if you're living in London like me and
it's
currently oh it's 6° outside at the
moment this morning it was minus 3 which
was just horrific but at least it's not
raining so you can see that on the
average year it's more or less it's
around 150 days uh the one on the far
right here that was last year and it was
a bit more than 150 days so if we look
at this we can say 150 rainy days a year
year that's we count that as failure
that means if there's 365 days in the
year which there isn't always then
there's 25 non-rainy days and we're
going to call that a success so that
gives us a success rate of 59% we can
say that 41% of the time it rains oops
dropped a pen
there so when you look out your window
and you're planning what to do for a
particular day let's say it's you know
middle of July do you think to yourself
oh maybe I need to take an umbrella
today because there's a 41% chance of
rain no of course you don't you look at
the sky clear sky it's sunny you think
not going to rain stay or maybe you look
at the app weather app and usually they
show you the the chance of rain and it
will be a different percentage each day
do you think that they're looking at
this and saying okay it's going to be
41% chance of rain no because it's going
to be different on a February to the day
in December to the day in July to when
the sky is covered in clouds to when
it's not and so on and so on it depends
on the context so we're using
probabilities to make these decisions in
our everyday life and it's not about in
this case this would be we can call this
success rate it's not about a success
rate it's about probability each day
we're taking on board context about the
situation to make those judgments and
there are many other ways that we use
probabilities in our everyday life like
when you see a car coming in a distance
and you're about to cross the road and
you're deciding can I make it across the
road before the car hits me you're using
probabilities when you're deciding
whether to take an umbrella when you're
looking out at the weather then you're
using probabilities when you're deciding
what time should I leave for work to
avoid the traffic you're using
probabilities there are so many ways
that you're using probabilities in your
everyday life and surprisingly we're
actually quite accurate at a lot of
these situations and we'll discuss that
later why that's the case how we get
more accurate it when we're not accurate
but more importantly for us you also use
already for your trading so here we just
have a random chart I think this was
Aussie dollar New Zealand dollar or
something so let's say that we go back
over the last 10 years and I'm going to
open a th trades like I'm going to go on
a simulator and I'm just going to spend
the weekend opening a th random trades
and what I'm going to do is I'm going to
open uh trades that are one to one risk
reward okay so risking one to make
one I'm going to open them at random
points on the chart I'm going to flip a
Point decide whether I'm going long or
short if it's heads I'm going long if
it's Tails I'm going short so after a th
trades what do you expect my results to
look like let's say that I'm not just
using like one chart like this because
obviously it could be influenced by
Trends but we going across 10 years so
that there are different Trends
different Market activity and so on I'm
going to open Ono one trades flipping a
coin to go long or short what do you
think well we can imagine that I'm going
to
lose trades 50% of the time and profit
50% of the time more or less like after
a th000 trades a large enough sample
size it should fall to this I've got no
Advantage cuz I'm flipping the coin so
it's just about distances if it's like
that I'm risking 30 Pips to make a
profit of 30 Pips for example okay it
should be about 50/50 but I'm obviously
going to lose money because of
transaction costs like the spreads and
so on but I think in a simulator you can
maybe even remove all that so if I
removed everything you'd say it's more
or less about 50%
would you take those traes would that be
a good strategy to follow of course not
stupid it would be a stupid strategy to
follow what if instead I did one
two
three so in this case I'm following the
advice of what people say when they say
trading game of probabilities therefore
you should do asymmetric risk return and
you could be wrong more times than
you're right and still make a profit
well what do we think if I'm flipping a
coin to decide whether to go long or
short and I'm just doing let's say
30 Pips against 90 Pips what are the
results going to be what do you think
they're going to be once again it's
going to be around Break Even because
there's no Advantage here so it's going
to hit this three times as often uh
sorry it's going to hit this three times
as often as it hits this which means
it's going to hit this 75% of the time
and it's going to hit this 25% of the
time okay so we can call these like I've
spoken about in previous videos our base
rates so our base rate is essentially
if we had no Edge in the market if we're
flipping a coin to go long or short and
doing over a long enough period of time
so that there's no advantage of like
Trends and stuff what would the
probabilities be those are our base
rates it's funny in one of the last
videos when I talked about probabilities
someone was complaining um there
actually two people that called me snake
oil and one said that this approach
sounds like snake oil and I was like
hold on a second so I'm giving you
something where you can measure your
Edge and it's objective and you're
saying it's snake oil compared to all of
the idiots out there who are using vague
entry and exit criteria keeping things
vague intentionally so you can't test
the approach giving you no means to test
their approach and somehow the one
that's being more precise and actually
testing it and giving you an approach
that you can use a scientific method
with is snake oil and then the other
person said this sounds is snake oil
because your base rates don't exist
they're just made up it's just this is
basic maths okay this just basic maths
there's nothing else to this I I mean
you you can just go and test it for
yourself if you don't believe it the
only thing that's made up here is that
I'm calling it The Base rid but you'll
understand why I call it the base rate
when we get on something a bit later
okay so you wouldn't take any of these
trades but for those of you who have
been trading up until the point you've
actually taken trades well you've taken
trades that are either a one: one or a
one to three or or some other scenario
that with a base rate would be giving
you a break even but for some reason
you've thought you've had some sort of
advantage so let's say for example that
uh I don't know I've got like a setup
where I'm going short here and I'm going
to put a stop loss up here which is my
one and I'm going to have a take profit
down here that's three okay 3 to one
trade like this if I'm taking this trade
I'm implicitly or indirectly making a
statement that I think the probabilities
are better than these so I think that
the chance of hitting the stop- loss the
one is less than 75% and therefore the
chance of hitting the the profit is more
than 25% okay so I've made an estimate
on probabilities there I've said the
probabilities are better than these but
if I'm not defining it if I'm not
measuring this or like actually defining
what the probability is then then I
can't get better at it I can't tell if
I'm accurate but you when you're taking
trades you're indirectly making a
statement about the probability saying
that they are better than base raids and
that's why you're taking the trade and
how do we know that because if all you
getting was the base rate probabilities
you wouldn't be taking the trade and if
your probabilities are worse were worse
than base rate you also wouldn't be
taking the trade CU you know you'd be
losing money overall so the fact you're
taking the trades means that you are
making an estimate of the probabilities
okay so both in your trading and in your
everyday life you're already estimating
probabilities you just are maybe not
consciously aware that you're doing
it okay so the next thing that people
say because now I've said okay we need
to be more specific about the
probabilties that we're estimating so
that we can measure how accurate we are
and improve and people say well it's you
can't do that it's impossible I can't
pick out like how can I say that this is
64% or something like that and I want to
show you that it is possible okay so
let's say that you have a trade oops
wrong thing here and you can test this
next time you're taking a trade I
encourage you to because this will be
the first step towards uh actually
estimating the probabilities so let's
say let's say that this lovely uptrend
like this and you think that this is
either the terminal point or at the very
least you're going to get one leg of the
wave here so you're going to enter a
trade here and let's say so we can keep
it in line with what we've just been
going through that this is going to be
uh 3 to one okay so your stop loss is up
here and that's one and your take profit
or like initial Target is down here and
that's three okay so one to three oops
risk
rewards now we know that the base rate
in this situation is going to be
25% and
75% so I'll say to you what percentage
chance do you think there is of a
profit
and what we want to get to is the point
where we can do something
called the equivalent bet
test oops
don't know what's going on with my
writing there
equivalent bet
test okay it's very difficult to write
and talk at the same time obviously I
can't multitask uh so this is something
that I believe it's name was Doug hubard
talks about in his books he also does a
lot of the calibration workshops and
stuff with people so he's like a a
leading expert on this but essentially
what we want to do is like let's say
that you you think the probability is
30%
okay so there's a 30% chance of a profit
therefore it will have positive
expectancy well then what I can do is
say okay
so we are going
to very bad let's say that this part
that
shaded is 30% and I say that if this
lands here you're going to make three
and if it lands here you're going to to
pay me one okay
and by the way if you couldn't tell by
my amazing drawing here this is like a
spinny wheel like The Wheel of Fortune
so this little white triangle is if if
it lands like if the wheel stops and
it's in the Shaded area you're going to
make three and if it's in the non-shaded
area you're going to pay me
one so if I say to you now which one do
you want to go for so we're going to be
betting real money like significant
money life-changing money do you want to
go for this this trade or do you want to
go for this wheel and let's say you
reply let's go for the
wheel and I say why and you say well
because I think there's probably a best
chance of it of getting the three well
in that case you've been overconfident
with your probability because you don't
actually think it's 30% because if you
thought it was 30% you wouldn't be
preferring to go for the wheel that is
30% on the other hand if you say me I
want to go for the trade then you've
been underconfidence with your
probability because you don't think it's
30% you think it's better than that
otherwise you would go for the wheel so
what you want to do is find the
percentage where they're equivalent
where it's an equivalent bet where you
don't care whether you go for the wheel
or whether you go for the trade okay now
a lot of people initially will say well
I have no [__] idea it could be 30%
it could be 50% for all I know so it's
just guessing and I would reply no it's
not guessing I'm might having a
conversation with someone in my head
here it's not guessing because we can
start with extremes so for example do
you think that there's a 100% chance so
let's get rid of this do you think
there's a 100% chance of the profit you
say no that's
absurd do you think there's a 90% chance
no that's absurd and so on and so on
until you sort of go from the 100% on
this side and you work your way down
until it's some somewhere here like 40%
or something like that
okay then we go from the other end do
you think there's a 0% chance no that's
absurd 20 30 and so on and you end up
with this this window where it could be
between these values let's say for
example that is going to be between
23% and uh
40% okay great now we've got our margin
of error so we can still track this we
can still take the trade or we can still
run this through the positive expectancy
calc calulation but we can just say okay
we're going to run this side and if that
happens okay we end up with negative
expectancy but the chance of that
happening compared to the rest like
there's there's a lot more that could
end up with a profitable outcome because
anything above 25% is going to be
profitable so maybe we accept that
margin of error there and take the trade
but at least we can start tracking
something and over time we'll get better
and better now this some of you would
already know what this is called and
therefore you will get why I said what I
said but this is called the Absurd
test and it's basically a lot of people
about the yes a lot of people will say I
don't know but people know more than
they think they know it's just that you
have to sort of you can start off by
ruling out what you know to not be true
or you know is absurd and end up with
something that's more reasonable then
from there you could say okay uh what
sort of what range would we have that
would give you a 95% confidence into for
or something like that and there are
ways we could test that but we won't get
into that for now I just want you to
understand that there are are ways that
we could get you to already nail down a
probability okay and that means if this
is the case somewhere deep in your
subconscious you have a probability and
that's how you're making this estimate
in the markets so let's say you end up
with this being 28% great now we can
track that and see over time how
accurate you are perfect then you can
start
improving but there's a problem okay
that if you're already doing these
probability estimates with your trades
the issue is that extensive Studies have
shown that people are not naturally
calibrated with their estimations and
here are a bunch of studies and there
are many more that have shown this just
in case you want to go and look it up if
you think I'm just making things up go
and check it out and what's been found
is that people are usually biased
towards either overconfidence or
underconfidence so remember in that last
example when I said about the equivalent
vet test that if you were preferring to
go for the spinning wheel you've been
overconfident with your estimations and
vice versa being underc confident so the
funny thing is that people are biased
towards one or the other but not like in
individual things it's not like okay in
trading I'm always overconfident and
this I'm underc confident it's like a
systemic thing it's that you're usually
overconfident in most things or usually
underc confident in most things and
so if we are not measuring what we're
doing and calibrating then you could be
overestimating or underestimating on on
these trades because Studies have shown
that you naturally will
be but the good news is that you can
improve on this so the first thing over
here we've got I think this guy's like a
a famous Las Vegas odds maker so there
are people like um Philip tetlock like
Doug hubard who I spoke about a minute
ago who run huge studies on forecasting
and for Philip tetlock it's the the
super forecasters with his good judgment
project with Doug hubard it's about like
taking groups of people and taking them
through calibration training I think he
gets paid by companies and what he
States is that there are certain groups
of people who are naturally better
calibrated than others for example
bookmakers the people who set odds for
like sports betting and stuff like that
the people who set those odds are
naturally or not naturally but in these
these groups that they they go through
this calibration training right at the
start they're better calibrated than
CEOs um and others that deal with
probabilities in their job are better
calibrated even when asked questions
that are unrelated to their job so it's
not that they're better calibrated just
in you know bookm it's that they're best
calibrated in general so they found that
once you go through calibration training
it doesn't just improve the one area
that you focused on for that it's going
to improve your ability to estimate
probabilities across the board in
anything so when you improve your
ability to estimate probabilities and
trading is going to impact and improve
other aspects of your life as well and
you'll see it once you go through all
this stuff you'll see it in everyday
life like someone oh it's funny one of
our members sent me a message saying and
he'll probably watch this and know it
was him but he I don't know I should
repeat this I think he said he was
sitting in a sauna going through the
probabilities of someone's towel
dropping or
something uh don't use probabilities in
that way because while you're sitting
there staring and trying to figure out
and go through the calculations they'll
probably be calling Security on you
saying he's staring at my
um chest we'll leave it at that
so that's the first thing that it is
possible it's been shown that you can
improve through calibration training and
it will improve all aspects of
probability estimates not just trading
and in this one this is fascinating so
this is from a study that was done by
John coats the former Trader now
neuroscientist does a lot of the studies
on trading and they were studying other
aspects of trading but through that
indirectly they were well not indirectly
they they were gathering this data and
indirectly made or came to another
conclusion so we can see here the sharp
ratios of all Traders than beginners and
experienced and what they realized is
that
overtime Traders improv their sharp
ratio so a sharp ratio is a measure of
how good you are at trading I mean I
think there are better ways but you know
it's an industry
standard so what they sort of what John
coat deduced from this or like his
conclusion was that this shows that is
possible to develop intuition in the
markets because you could be using the
same strategy or whatever but your sharp
ratio improves over your career so
something has improved so I believe this
is not from John coat this is what I
have sort of taken from this is that
what is intuition well in the case of
the markets I'd say intuition is
implicit learning so
there's implicit
knowledge and explicit
knowledge and obviously the implicit
knowledge and explicit knowledge becomes
knowledge by implicit or explicit
learning explicit knowledge is what most
of you watching this have for trading
right now which is rules techniques
things that you could explain out loud
about your trading oh this is how you
read a so and so indicator this is how I
look for a nonsense Head and Shoulders
pattern so I have to get these digs in
there where I can makes me feel good
about myself
it's just you know simple things in life
sad little life we live then the
implicit knowledge is the stuff that you
can't quite explain and actually in the
research it's defined this should be a
quote because it's actually quotes from
the research it's defined as being a
deep understanding of the statistical
structure of event sequences now maybe
I'm stretching a little bit here but how
else could we describe this would it not
be that it's about understanding the pro
or being able to estimate the
probabilities of
situations I think so so I think that
John coat's study shows that since most
people are estimating like when we when
we take a trade we're estimating the
probabilities okay we're saying it's
better than base rate and the more
experience you get the better you get at
doing that so they're developing their
ability but I bet you if they measured
it and did the calibration to improve it
they develop their sharp ratio even
quicker and you're going to do that and
you're going to prove me right because
you're going to get amazing at trading
and you're going to say it was all
because I started to track my
probabilities and estimate them and
calibrate now this whole thing of
implicit and explicit learning I've seen
it mentioned um we talked about
extensively in our our program and I've
seen it mentioned a few times in some
trading videos but there are ways that I
don't unless you go through the research
there are things that I think people are
missing and there are some really really
fascinating studies on this that prove
just how important it is to develop
implicit knowledge and you are
developing it you know you will be
developing it with your trading but you
see the more that you focus on the
explicit side which everything on social
media that you see where it's like this
is how you trade the fair value Gap and
you're doing the fair value Gap wrong
because you should be looking for this
thing and all of these little rules it's
just like stacking rules on top of rules
and pattern recognition and stuff all of
this is just making you rely more and
more on explicit knowledge and you're
never developing the implicit knowledge
or not as much as you could because of
how much you're trying to look for
things like you're just playing an adult
version of where's Wally or where's
wildo rather than actually developing a
skill but there's studies done on it's
called an SRT so serial reaction time
test and essentially what they have is
like four lights like this and each
light has a corresponding button and
when it lights up you press the button
and they measure your reaction time so
when it's a sequence like it was like du
d d du every time then you'd know so
your reaction 's quicker and when it's
random completely your reaction time is
slower then they do interesting things
like they do a sequence that people
can't consciously pick up on so if I if
it's a sequence and I ask you to explain
a sequence you probably haven't even
realized it's a sequence it's quite a
complex one but subconsciously you've
picked up on it and it's improved your
reaction time then they have complex
sequences which are muddied by
Randomness so definitely someone can't
consciously detect it and they still see
improved reaction time and it's showing
how uh you've through implicit learning
can pick up on these patterns even in
amongst Randomness which relates to the
market because in the markets at least
with what we believe with the D Market
Theory there are some movements which um
are predictable and there are some
movements that are random this when the
markets are in steady state so when it's
not reacting to uh repricing based on on
information um so there's a mix of
random and deterministic and we can pick
up on the deterministic parts even even
amongst the randomness because of what
we're seeing in the the SRT test anyway
that's a whole topic for another time so
how do we
improve the skill how do we develop it
so there are 10 points here and these
have been taken from a mix of um the
sort of literature and the the the
groups the decision psychologists that
focus on this area and do the studies so
it's the points that they've put
together I've sort of combined things
from different places the ones that I
think apply to trading and also Alo from
my own experience and from working with
traders to know which ones are actually
applicable so we're going to go through
each of these uh one by one some of them
we won't need to go through that that in
much detail so it won't take too long
hopefully and I just want to point out
just down here say in the description
box there's a link to our free training
and you also find links to other free
resources that we have now the free
training I'm actually recording a new
version of it soon a completely
different training but the one that's on
there right now at the time of filming
this there are similarities to what
we're going through in this session I'd
still recommend watching it all but sign
up anyway because after that training I
also send you lots more training for
different areas of your trading stuff
that's deeply researched evidence-based
extensively tested based on my
experience and the stuff that we give
away for free I know this is a bit of a
cliche but we make sure it's much better
than people's paid or free stuff because
we genuinely want you to get value from
the things you're learning so it's not
like a glorified sales process or
something um so sign up for the training
anyway even though it's going through
similar things because that way I can
send you any new free trainings that I
put together resources and stuff you'll
get all of them and there's a lot that
you're going to get so go and do that I
said I was only going to ask you one
thing which is to watch all of this and
if you have questions to ask me and
stuff but I'm asking you another thing
which is to sign up okay I just had to
stop the recording and start it again
cuz I'm absolutely petrified of some
issue going on and me losing all of this
explanation okay so the first point is
that we don't want to use vague language
we want to be specific when we say
specific that means using a number for
the percentages so where's my pen gone
we want to use a
number meaning 75%
75% one of our members complains about
the way I do my fives it's just how we
are taught at school you you do this bit
then you put the Hat on top that's how
we were taught it's like 75% 76% if you
want to get really really precise you
could do
76.2% or something and you might say
that's crazy well you don't need to get
that granular but actually there are
studies that have been done on this
again and they've shown through super
forecasters so people who are really
calibrated with their their probability
estimates that actually the smaller the
the differences in probabilities that
actually has an impact on the accuracy
the level of accuracy I'm not explaining
it very well just off the top of my head
like this but um but if you if you
really want to have the information then
I'll I'll give it to you in the comments
just let me know so this what you can
see on screen here is a study that was
done at the CIA with with intelligence
analysts and what they were studying is
well are these what they call words of
estimative probability so what they
found was that you know at the CIA
they're analyzing complex information
and then having to come up with
probabilities of different scenarios
potentially playing out and these
scenarios can have a huge impact on the
world it can have an impact on decisions
about whether it's go to war or things
like that and so they started to realize
that when people are using words like
that's probably going to happen or it's
likely to happen people are interpreting
them differently and if people are
interpreting them differently then that
means that they might come to the wrong
conclusion so before they switched to
doing numbers they did this study and
they asked people okay with these words
what percentage probability would you
put this as and look at the wide ranges
between each of these words but you know
what I think is really worrying is that
these intelligence analyst
obviously they're they're putting
together the intelligence but they
should be intelligent as well and I
really wonder what absolute nut jobs are
working at the CIA who think that
there's a 100% probability when someone
is put improbable or little chance means
90% are they absolutely insane or look
at the other end almost certain what's
that about
3% get these people out of there these
are these people are the reasons that
governments make the disastrous
decisions that they do sometimes get
them out of there anyway um this shows
you like with your own trading if you
say oh it's fairly likely it'll be a
profit but that's not good enough
because one you can't measure that two
over time you will adjust those
probabilities to be something that's
more favorable for you again that's
something that's been studied where
people um assess How likely they think
something is I think it was it was done
there was a study in like the' 70s or
something on uh some sort of event
involving Russia uh we mention it in the
program but I can't remember exactly
what it was but they they saw that after
the event people's reflection of what
they thought How likely they thought it
was it becomes more favorable so if an
event did happen then the probability
percentage increases from like the the
word that they stated and if it doesn't
happen it decreases and you will do the
same because we're all human and we're
all susceptible to these things because
we like to be right and our brain has
this narrative machine that creates
narratives that makes us right and
connects the world around us and so on
and so on but it's not helpful for your
trading you need to overcome those silly
meat robot Tendencies and um it's also
like not only is it that you can't
measure things properly but also when
you take a trade today compared to six
months from now and both of them were
likely to be a profit uh we move that
then you're going to in your mind it
could be a completely different
probability but we need to be specific
about these things otherwise how can we
improve how can we know that what we're
doing is is the right thing so don't use
vague language be specific you need to
start using numbers even if you start
off with broad numbers and get more and
more granular As you move on so starting
off with the tens moving it to the fives
then getting to the ones and then if you
want to be a complete odd born start
doing a
0.02% then up to
you the next thing is that you need
training on forecasting and estimating
probabilities so funly enough what we're
going through right now is training on
forecasting and estimating probabilities
so Philip Tech Len the good judgment
project found that just from one
training session on estimating
probabilities people were more accurate
with estimating probabilities because
you know it's not just about uh
developing the skill of estimating
probabilities obviously that is going to
have a big impact on how accurate you
are it's also about the techniques that
you use the Frameworks to
actually so the way that some of these
techniques and Frameworks work it's not
that they then dramatically improve um
how to word this in a way that makes
sense they're basically helping you to
think in the right way to get the
information that you already have in
mind and apply it in the right way for
the the probability estimate that's what
they're for it's not that they're going
to actually do it for you they're
helping you to use your brain in the
right way which you wouldn't already be
doing or at least not to this extent so
what you can see on screen here is bases
theorem or Bas
rule bases rule
and I know that if you're not used to
formulas and stuff then this can look a
bit
complicated and you know it's probably
more complicated than we need it to be
we can keep things really simple and
essentially what we're going to be
looking at is we are going to start with
what we call a base rate which is why
now you'll figure out that's why I call
those Pro those probabilities if you
have no Edge the base rate so you start
off with a base rate it's also known as
a prior and then what you're effectively
doing is taking all the information that
you know about the situation okay so if
you think the base rate is that there's
no Edge then you're taking all the
information that you know like the
variables and ending up with what we
call a posterior so you have a prior and
a posterior but we we'll just say base
rate and what we call it is just
adjusted
probability okay so that's essentially
what you're doing you're taking a
logical St stting point and ending up
with something that's adjusted with the
variables if you if you like um
behavioral psychology and Daniel caraman
I think he would refer to this as the
inside
view then you apply this the outside
View and then you end up with like the
final
probability
so this is not like for some reason when
we talk about these probability
estimates and going through this process
with trading people think it's insane
like how can you do that in the markets
you can't predict what's going to happen
in the markets blah blah blah but I mean
I've just told you about the CIA who are
analyzing really complex situations with
lots of moving parts and coming up with
probability estimates for different
scenarios in scenario planning in
business and different things where you
have these decision trees you come up
with probabilities of the different
things happening it's how we should be
applying things in the market and how
the very best Traders would be and if
you want to be lazy then you won't do it
but if you want to be accurate and
better at trading you will do it and so
just to give you an example if we think
about weather so we talked about earlier
uh that depressing chart of how many
days in the UK it rained now we saw that
there was a success rate of 59% so 41%
of the time it rained but when you look
at the weather app and it tells you the
percentage chance of rain it's not just
applying those percentages that would be
ridiculous likewise when you're looking
at your trading with every trade you
shouldn't just be applying your success
rate why because the context matters and
the context is going to be different in
each situation and that's going to
change the probabilities so here we've
got two screenshots one from the US
weather organization and one from the UK
weather organization whatever the hell
they're called and they're talking about
how they
forecast um the weather it's complex
constantly changing
situation and on the UK side they say
there are three important stages knowing
what the weather is doing now
calculating how this will change in the
future and using their expertise to
refiner details so I've highlighted a
few things this says in order to know
what the weather will do in the future
we first need to know accurately what
it's doing now now anyone who's a member
of the D Trader development program I
hope you're having a light bulb moment
and realizing this relates to what we
talk about is the phases of a trading
system okay so these are called
observations what it's currently doing
now then they have supercomputers which
use these observations as starting
conditions base rate for very complex
equations that predict where the weather
will move and how it will evolve as time
goes on then they work around the clock
to check the forecast see if it's going
to plan if it's not they'll amend any
forecast going out to customers so what
they're essentially doing is as
information comes to light they're
adjusting this so their adjusted
probability or their posterior becomes
their prior or their base rate and gets
adjusted as they go along so it's like a
constant like tweaking of
things and like they give an example if
the temperature is slightly lower than
expected that could mean the difference
of having Frost at the end of the night
or not so it changes the what's
anticipated or on the US side they say
whether forecasts are made by collecting
data about the current state of the
atmosphere using an understanding of
atmospheric processes to predict how the
atmosphere will evolve before any
forecast can be made a meteorologist
must first understand what the current
weather conditions are and what's
producing them that's important what is
producing them when all this
data uh review and Analysis completed
over time meteorologists have provide
the means to track the evolution of
front Jets Cyclones and anti Cyclones
and use this information for pattern
recognition Okay so let me just explain
what our members would understand when I
talk about the phases of our trading
system we talk about first understanding
what's happened in the past interpreting
the current situation in light of
understanding what's happened in the
past and then anticipating what may
happen in the future it goes in that
order you have to understand the past to
be able to interpret the current
situation to be able to anticipate the
future because it's a sequence of cause
effects and it's not enough to know what
is happening now it's also you need to
know the Dynamics of that what's causing
What's Happening Now what's caused it so
that's what we go through in our system
and we end up with primary analysis
where we're looking at what's happened
in the past secondary analysis where
we're looking at potential outcomes and
uh estimating probabilities and that
leads us to our
entry so this is what they're doing with
the weather it's all about context
they're gathering information about the
context to make predictions about the
future and that's exactly what we do in
the markets so this is dollar Frank okay
I made a stupid mistake here so I'm
filming this a little bit later on in
the video when we've got to another
example and I've realized it's the next
example is the trade on dollar Frank
that I took this what you can see here
is I think the same chart as before it's
the Aussie dollar New Zealand dollar so
everything I'm saying about taking the
trade just ignore that and just make it
like that's a hypothetical trade and
later I'll show you the trade that I
took which it looks very similar
actually and that's why I got confused
but yeah it's not a trade that I took
it's a hypothetical one and I took a
trade on dollar Frank well I pointed out
the entry on one of my live stream
trading sessions the entry was going to
be at the close of that day and at the
close of that day we got the exact what
we were looking for and I enter the
trade so I enter the trade
long here okay so what do we need to be
able to plug this into our expectancy
calculation to figure out whether this
could be a trade or not we need to know
the potential outcomes and then estimate
the probabilities of them so I'm going
to just cut the cut a long story short
with the potential outcomes and say that
in this case the potential outcomes it
was going to be about here to about here
and it was more or less like a four or
five to one okay and if you need a
method of trading that allows you to
estimate outcomes in a meaningful way
because technically the price at any
point could do anything right it can
move up five ticks then down three and
then up another two and you need to know
where the meaningful outcomes are and a
lot of methods of trading don't have
that they make it vague like oh whenever
this pattern comes up just enter us a 10
one but that's not taken into account
the context your outcomes have to be
based on the context and since we know
prices move in the markets from this
relationship of volume and liquidity and
changes in price movements will happen
when that balance between the two
changes then we can say that an end of
an outcome is likely to be at a point
where we'd expect a shift in activity a
change in that balance in some way and
that's what we try to identify with the
way that I trade at least and I think
that's how we should be trading everyone
should be trading that well not I mean
if you're using technical analysis that
should be the focus so your potential
outcom shouldn't be arbitrary they
should be based on something that then
is measurable in some way or is like a
defined point that gives you a way of
estimating the probability
like if I dropped someone in the middle
of London and I said what do you think
the probability is of them ending up on
in a location in West London compared to
East London I'm only this is such a
random anergy but it was from one of our
free training things a while ago and I
said okay well what do you think the
probability is of one or the other well
you said I don't know how long is a
piece of string like what location in
east or west London like how far cuz if
one is like 10 miles away and the
other's 2 miles away it's more likely
they're going to end up at one 2 miles
away
anyway sorry they getting sidetracked
but I feel these things are important to
explain so I end up with with this let's
let's say that it was a 4 to one to make
it easy for the calculations here okay
so first of all I def find the
outcomes so we have 1 to four which
means that now when I go to the
probability estimates I know there's a
base rate here of 20% here and 80% here
why because it's likely to hit this 4
times as often as this so that's
8020 now that is the start of the sort
of version of Bas rule that we use the
prior and now I can take in all of the
information from the situation so this
hadn't happened yet okay so we're just
down here so I can look at for example
how we look at it I'm looking at three
broad areas the structure um the
significant levels of path resistance
then the micro structure which can
include like order flow that kind of
thing so we're looking at volume the
shortterm Trend and momentum that kind
of thing and I can look I can break down
all of these individual aspects and
adjust the base rate probabilities based
on that information some adjustments up
some adjustments down now the only way
that is possible to do this is if you
actually have a way to differentiate and
Define each of the aspects and we'll get
on to that in a second um so like a a
price move like how do you define and
differentiate because not all price
moves are the same so we'll cover that
in more detail in a second but basically
by making these adjustments I could end
up with the the probabilities that I can
put in the expectancy calculation and I
can tell is it a trade yes or no then I
can use the probabilities or the
expectancy calculation to decide how
much to risk and then I can take the
trade which I did do and ends up being
nice profitable trade uh something like
between four and 5% profit lovely and in
a way that could be measured and we can
see over time how accurate I am with
it so this is the process we go
through but there are ways to improve
and one way is to get more accurate base
rates so if we're starting off with a
base rate that's just based on if you
didn't have an edge what if there are
particular scenarios where you know that
the base rate can be slightly different
for example if you're with Trend counter
Trend maybe the base rate is slightly
different for each of those that you can
see that okay from tens of thousands of
Trades that I've taken um or that I've
gathered that when it's with the trend
instead of the original base rate I had
it's actually a slice adjustment of
three right off the bat okay that's my
base rate then maybe if you believe in
the chart patterns and stuff like that
maybe it's with Head and Shoulders or
some other nonsense that there's a
different base rate you you get the idea
there could be different types of Base
rates okay so for some reason there was
a problem with the original recording
for the section so I'm having to
re-record it so you'll understand if it
sounds a little bit different uh but
this research is really fascinating
so this was done in the 1990s by a guy
called Joshua tenel and his team he was
a professor of cognitive science at MIT
and he was doing this huge research
project to understand the Casual ways
that people make predictions in their
everyday life and so he got like groups
of students and asked them to make
predictions about things such as uh
people's lifespans movie run times poem
length how long it takes to bake a cake
all these sorts of things like things
that you maybe wouldn't necessarily nor
off the top of your head but you could
Hazard a guess at and so in this top
section we can see what the actual
distributions were the empirical
distributions of these different things
and then the bottom section here these
are the results of people's predictions
and shockingly they were incredibly
accurate on average so the distributions
of people's answers when they were asked
to predict these things were very
similar to the actual distributions so
we've got different distribution types
here different distribution shapes if
you want to think of it that way and the
distribution of people's answers
followed a similar distribution shape
whether it was um you know like a
balance distribution power law
distribution you can kind of see a
description of it down here and what
they figured out is that it seems that
the way we make predictions is by using
something that they
called basian
cognition and so if we think about B
rule that we went through for a moment
ago what we're essentially doing is
going through that in our minds and the
reason they call it basan cognition is
because if you're going to use a
computer to come up with these same
predictions then that computer would
have to go through some sort of
variation of basis Rule and that's
essentially what we're doing we're
taking some sort of reference point
initially so a prior and then we're
making adjustments based on um
information that we have about the
situation so for example this is an
example that was given in a book that I
was reading about this this um study if
you are talking to one of your male
friends and they say that they're going
out for dinner that night then you might
think well majority of their friends are
male so there's a high probability that
they're going out for dinner with
another man but if they point out that
oh I'm going out for dinner with someone
from work and you know that most of the
people on their team at work are female
then you would adjust the probabilities
based on that so it's without even
thinking about it we're making these
adjustments based on the information
that we have we have an initial base
rate and we make these adjustments now
the thing that's in interesting with
this study for this point number three
of getting more accurate base rates is
that some of the questions the people
answering on average got the right
distribution such as the one about
Pharaoh so this distribution
here is what they had in their answers
so it's be more specific the actual
question they were asked here was
something along the lines of if an
Egyptian pharaoh has been in power for
11 years how much longer will they rule
for and so the distribution of their
answers ends up being correct which
meant that they were making the right
adjustments based on the information
they have that he's been in power for 11
years but actually although the
distribution was correct the age overall
was wrong they were predicting that the
Pharaoh would be much older than what
the real distribution was and the reason
for that is that they were using the
wrong base rate they were basing their
answer on their knowledge of European
kings and queens or more modern kings
and queens rather than pharaoh and the
problem is that Pharaoh would have had a
much shorter lifespan I think the
average lifespan was something like in
the 30s rather than you know 50s or 60s
or whatever people were predicting here
so with just a few pieces of information
we can make quite accurate predictions
but if the initial base rate the prior
is wrong then the whole thing is going
to be inaccurate even if we make the
adjustments in the right way to the
right extent the overall judgment the
overall prediction is going to be
inaccurate so it's getting the base rate
right that's so important now there's
something called the base rate fallacy
which is where people don't think about
the base rate when they're answering
something and there's this famous excise
or question that's from Daniel Carman he
did studies on this where he's talking
about this description of someone where
they he says there's something along the
lines of um they're shy and quiet they
like spending time on their own reading
on so on and what profession do you
think they are a farmer or a librarian
and most people will choose a librarian
because the description matches what
they have in their mind as a librarian
but this is the base rate fallacy in
play because if we think about it a
different
way we could start off by
saying how many farmers are there in the
world and how many Librarians are there
in the world and it's going to be
something like this librarians
Farmers something like that of the
Librarians how many of them would match
the description like maybe you generous
and say okay it's maybe this many like
three quarters how many for Farmers
maybe you being not very generous and
saying oh it's only this much because
they're actually all very extroverted
which I don't believe well this
percentage of this amount is still
smaller than this percentage of this
amount so by ignoring the base rate and
thinking about the conditional part so
ignoring what should be the prior and
thinking about the variable information
Parts you're coming to the wrong
conclusion pigeon's just come and sat on
my window still here going to come and
get a free lesson here so when we talk
about uh with people's trading this can
play out in many different ways because
if they start off by thinking about
what's in favor of the trade in that
situation oh momentum's running out is
hitting this path of resistance or
whatever then it's likely that they're
going to be estimating based on those
aspects and ignoring the base rate which
is that but hold on a second this is a
10 to1 trade you can't say it's more
likely to be a profit than not they're
not I'm talking one 10 trade one risk 10
return it's not going to be more likely
to be a profit than a loss regardless of
all these other factors like it's going
to take a [__] huge situation to
overcome those probabilities to make it
more likely you end up with a profit and
yet a lot of Traders do that you know I
see not that I go on brain RW Instagram
trading social uh trading hash tag stuff
but I looked at them for something we
were doing a little while ago and lo of
them are like this 10 to one thing has
like 75% success rate and you're like
you are so stupid but the people that
are agreeing with you in the comments
and believing it I don't know if they
are naive or they're also stupid or what
that's not very nice of me to say that
they're not stupid they're just lovely
innocent people so that's the base rate
fallacy the second thing that people and
and by the way this also applies when
you you use your success rate as the
probabilities but that one also ties in
with the anchoring effect the anchoring
effect is basically when you're asked to
estimate something um whatever number
you start from that's going to become an
anchor so if you start from the base
rate as it should be and make
adjustments you're more likely to be
accurate if you start from your success
rate then you're less likely to be
accurate so let's say that the base rate
at least like how we've been doing them
earlier in this video
is showing that there's a I keep doing
that that's showing that there's a 30%
probability okay but your success rate
is
55% and so you decide to start from here
and make your
adjustments or like you you're going to
adjust down from there until the point
that you with your equivalent bet thing
you're happy you're going to end up with
a much higher probability from starting
from there than you would from starting
with 30% even if you're looking at the
exact same situation called the
anchoring effect okay so I say like okay
there's a trade here let's say I take
two groups of people 100 Traders 100
people that watching this on each side
hopefully there's 100 200 people
watching this that we can split it up
and on one side I say okay I'm going to
start a countdown thing from 100% And I
want you to stop this when you think
it's the probability of this trade being
a profit and the other ones I'm going to
say okay we're going to start from 0%
and move up from there and you'll see
that these percentage uh probabilities
going to be lower than these ones just
the anchoring effect so you got be
really careful with that since the base
rates are so important you got to start
with the right base rate have accurate
base rates the next thing is to break
the situation or the problem down more
effectively so we have the base rate
then we're looking at all the variable
information that influen the base or
adjusts the base rate end up with the
end adjusted probability so first of all
this lovely guy over here uh his name is
enrio fery and you may have heard of him
probably oh right en Rico fery you
probably haven't heard of him in terms
of probabilities probably more to do
with science but he used to come up with
problems interesting questions that I
used to this day in like interview
processes at Google and places like that
where they ask you a question that no
sane person has the answer to but the
whole point is that you can break it
down to try and figure out like a good
guesstimate so it's not about like when
you have a problem or a situation you
have to estimate something to say I
don't know there will always be some
things that you do know so there's an
example I think it was given in Philip
tetlock's book about there's a question
of I think it might have been from enrio
fery the question is how many piano
tuners are there in Chicago something
like that you go [__] if I know like
who the hell would know that um what the
you start off by saying what do I think
the pro the the population is in Chicago
and you might also say I don't know cuz
I don't know either but you might think
okay is there a city I do know the
population of and how does it compared
to that so maybe you know the population
of New York and you know how more or
less what the population is like of
Chicago in comparison to that and you
can think okay how many pianos are there
likely to be is percentage of that how
many people have pianos and how many
piano tuners do you need for each piano
or like how many pianos can be covered
by one piano tuner you know a piano tuna
is not just like a like technique or
like a tool it's a person that comes and
tunes the piano no jokes about tuna fish
um and he ends up with like the the end
conclusion and so it's the same with the
markets where if I say what is the
probability of this situation you could
say I don't know but there are things
that you do know there are aspects of it
that you can say are different to other
situations or making it more or less
likely that particular move is going to
happen Okay so you start with what you
do know what do you know about the
situation what can you change the
probabilities based on and then you
leave the rest at base rate so you
adjust for those probabilities or you
use those to start figuring out other
adjustments that you can make oh if
that's like that and that's like that
that must mean that is like that and so
on then we see this always fascinates me
these are uh Inuit people and they're
building out of snow or ice and there's
that famous factoid that um in the
Western in Western languages we
generally have one word for snow and
Inuits have hundreds actually it's more
like dozens uh and it's not so
straightforward as like they have dozens
of words for it but they do
differentiate different types of snow
differently to us we we don't really
differentiate you know here in the UK If
you have snow really it's just you
either build a snowman or it's it's like
one snowflake is going to cause all the
public transport to come to a halt and
everyone's going to have snow day like
that's the extent of it for us we're not
out there building EG glues and whatever
else so for them because they are using
snow and ice for so many different
things like building and different tools
or
whatever they need the words to describe
the different sorts because they're
important variables so if you have
important variables you need to be able
to differentiate between them so these
are the two points I want us to keep in
mind when we look at the chart again so
if we think about this was
um this was the trade I took so the same
exact chart or have we changed something
here just okay so this little Gap in
between there was where I went and
refilmed a bit from earlier where I'd
made the mistake with the previous
example which is just embarrassing but
I'm not going to go back and explain
everything all over again so this was
the trade that I took on dollar Frank
and as I was explaining
earlier you see how the situation was
similar so I could tell like the stop
loss was here I was looking at it before
thinking that doesn't look like a four
or five to one um but I was like but
it's the right chart so it must be but
anyway this is the one so this is the
one and it's like a four or five to one
so just keep things easier like we were
doing earlier we're basically doing the
same thing as before but uh 80% chance
it should be the other way around so %
chance of loss and 20% chance of return
so it should be the other way around
okay so you know earlier when I was
explaining it and I was talking about we
start off with the base rate that's this
and then we're making different
adjustments well we need different ways
to differentiate stuff so when you look
at a situation that you're potentially
trading there are factors that are
influencing you to think that that's a
potential trade opportunity there are
reasons that you're saying without
explicitly stating the the probabilities
but when you're deciding to take the
trade
there are things that are making you
think the probabilities are better than
base rate so you need to be able to
differentiate and Define those so for
example if you've got a path of
resistance like this and you've got the
exact same situation in two parallel
universes but with one of them the price
approaches it like this and in one of
them the price approaches it like this
really direct move you know that one is
more likely to reverse and one's more
likely to break out compared to the
other like this one is maybe more likely
to reverse then if this has got momentum
I mean it still could reverse but it's
just the probabilities are different
right and likewise if you're looking at
order flow you know from the what what's
showing on the footprint chart you know
from what's in the order book um if
you're looking at volume profile you
know from where you are in the profile
and various other aspects like whatever
it is that you're using to trade if you
think the thing is Meaningful there are
things that you're you're counting as
variables in a situation or at least you
should be and if you're counting them as
variables that are influencing whether
you should take the trade or not or
influencing the likelihood of the the
trade being a profit you need to
differentiate and Define them so for
example when we're looking at structure
we have uh structure
characteristics which basically the
speed
length and depth of
pullback now that sounds basic and you
know is basic there are other ways we
can get more complex of it and there are
more complex explanations I can give a
it but just to keep things more simple
for now okay so now when I look at a
structure I have some ways of defining
and differentiating between it so I
could look at this shortterm downwards
move here and compare it to this and I
could describe the difference between
them using these okay so I could look at
a write up of a trade without even
seeing the charts and understand what's
being described from these things and
that's not just for the sake of it it's
not because I want to read writeups of
Trades it's so that you can start making
adjustments for the probabilities and
measuring over time how accurate you are
with them likewise for a path of
resistance we're looking at strength and
dependability when we're looking at um
the micro structure at the time of Entry
we're looking at a combination of the
trend momentum and volume uh and there
are other things but if there's
something that's related to your trades
that's related to your way of analyzing
the markets and what you believe is the
underlying principle of the markets you
need to be able to differentiate between
them and describe them so you need to
figure out how to start breaking those
things down start making an effort to
actually do
that then we've already covered this but
you can always go through the equivalent
bet test and the absurdity test so let's
say that you've made your adjustments to
your probabilities then at the end
you're like you have this final
probability is 64% okay brilliant let's
take your 64 % and let's put it into uh
the equivalent bet test and say like
this is going to be 64% which would you
rather take this or the trade and again
you could say I'd rather take this I'd
rather take the trade that was really
bad shading I took a lot more care of my
shading earlier and even that was
terrible but that could be the final
test because the thing is if you're
making adjustments for individual
aspects of the trades like okay I'm
going to do a plus 1% probability for
this aspect of the trend and plus 2% for
this bin minus 0.5 for this bin and so
on the conclusion you might have got to
a somewhat robotic way of doing these
individual adjustments and when you run
it through the equivalent bet test you
might think oh actually that's a bit
higher I don't think it actually like
these all together combined to lead to
this probability adjustment so I always
say to our members that it's important
to assess the individual aspects of the
trade but all of them combined to give
the overall context a situation and
they're not having an individual impact
on the the trade they're all like it's
almost like words in a sentence that
together they're giving the meaning the
context of that situation but you don't
interpret each individual words and
figure out what they mean and then try
and jam it all together that's kind of
what the old school translators used to
do like from uh Spanish to English or
something you'd end up with this
convoluted sentence so instead it's like
they combine to give a context and so it
might be if you approach the the um
probability adjustments in more of a
robotic way what you end up with is far
off what you'd actually be comfortable
with so by running through the
equivalent bet test it can make it much
easier and again the absurdity test you
can also do this on the individual
aspects so let's say you're looking at a
certain movement or a certain thing in
an indicator that you're relying on you
don't know what to adjust the
probability by for that particular thing
instead you can start with the absurdity
test do I think it affects the
probability by 20% no that's absurd 10%
7% well it's between 2 and 6% okay it's
quite broad but we can start with that
and over time collecting the data we can
start to refine it and refine it as you
get better at estimating probabilities
as you have more data to use as a
reference point and each individual
situation as a reference point you see
something happens like let's say that
I'm looking at situation A okay assessed
all this and then I've got situation B
and situation A I thought that was uh 5%
adjustment for a particular thing and
then situation B was like weaker and it
was therefore like a 2% adjustment then
I have situation C and I go well it's
not as strong as that situation it's not
as weak as that situation if that was
five and that was two then this one must
be like
3.5 and the more of these situations you
have over time in your
head you start to builds up these these
this database of patterns I don't mean
traditional chart patterns I mean your
pattern recognition machine in your mind
that you can start to more accurately uh
give these probabilities if we think
back to the implicit knowledge that I
was talking about
earlier so it comes from experience as
well then consider potential issues so
this could be things that you haven't
considered so for example when we had
the pandemic going on and any headline
was moving prices a lot or when it was
the start of the Russia Ukraine war or
Russia invasion um
any headlines would change prices
dramatically so during that situation
you might think well these are the
probability adjustments I've got however
there's this big unknown variable that
could dramatically change things so I
need to maybe have a wider margin of
error here so let's say that my end
probability is 35% but that could adjust
things either way maybe 5% so it's going
to be between 30 and 40% something like
that um that's percent side not
multiplication or it might be that
you're breaking down a situation and
[Music]
you you're basing things on like an
indicator down here and moving average
and then you look at the price move and
it's high momentum and you think to
yourself I've got no way of of
estimating the probability of that or
making a probability adjustment based on
that so I might write down that a
potential issue is that I I'm not able
to Define trends
SL price
move and that might be a limiting factor
that makes me have no confidence in
taking that particular trade at that
point in time but now I know okay I need
to figure out how can I start analyzing
this better what aspects of my system or
in my Approach do I need to change or
what skill do I need to develop here so
you consider all the potential issu
issues issues so why it feels like I
can't say that word properly issues
issues whatever so that you know one how
to improve two what could go wrong with
the probability estimate where it might
be inaccurate and three whether you need
to have that margin of error and and
many other things as well but we can
move on from that one okay so let's say
that you have uh the different ways of
differentiating the different aspects
and you have been estimating your
probabilities well the next thing is
that we need to be consistent with it
and this is a bigger problem than you
might think so there was a lot of
research done by this guy here Paul me
and I'm sure you've all heard of Daniel
caraman So Daniel caraman was influenced
by some work that Paul me did looking at
the consistency or the accuracy of
expert judgment and you'll be able to
find online a lot of stuff lot of
studies and stuff on Expert
judgment ex they do it without an e and
I'm sure in the UK we add an e here but
I'm going to do it like that because
that's what you'll find for the studies
what they found is that in many cases
uh a
formula or you think for like an
algorithm but this like before like
proper technology and stuff uh but a
formula can outperform expert judgment
and they're looking at like um judging
wines and different things like that and
essentially it's because we there are
many reasons but experts or anyone but
experts what matters here will assess
and process information differently at
different points in time so for example
if there's when we say judgment it's
about like it's not like where there's a
black and white answer it's where you
have to give an opinion a judgment
assessment or something so with experts
if you give them the same situation to
judge at two completely separate points
in time where the second point of time
they've forgotten about the first time
they're likely to give slightly
different judgments okay so it's lacking
consistency and this is what will happen
in the markets if you give someone a
situation that they are perfectly
capable of analyzing so they've got the
cap abilities to analyze that and you
ask them to give you a probability
estimate now and then you ask them 5
years from now when they can't remember
about the last time they'll most likely
give you different probabilities maybe
they'll be in the right ballpark but
they'll be different off by even if it's
1% it'll be slightly different maybe not
on that individual trade maybe if give
them 10 of them you'll see a lot of them
they'll be different so what can we do
about this well it's all about the order
we process information in and the
waiting that we give to different
information like we might wait the
impact of them differently from one
occasion to another now we can't
completely get rid of that but we can
alleviate it to a certain extent and it
comes from your trading system so if you
think back to earlier when I said
imagine you could accurately estimate
probabilities you wouldn't need a
trading system where you're following
some criteria to enter a trade or not
because as long as you can Define the
potential outcomes and estimate the
probabilities of them therefore you can
figure out if the trade has a positive
or negative expectancy you could trade
any situation so we need a trading
system then well what I believe a
trading system is for is to make you
more efficient at finding the
opportunities and that's not something
we'll discuss this time but they also
make you more consistent and since the
aim is to be consistently profitable I.E
being profitable by using a consistent
repeatable process and it all comes down
to consistently estimating the
probabilities accurately or is
consistent level of accuracy the system
is going to allow you to do that cuz the
system shouldn't just be for like a lot
of people think of a system as being the
criteria you follow for knowing when to
enter a trade or when to scale in and
scale out instead it should be a lot
more focused on the analysis and the
Order of that analysis to ensure that
you're processing information in a
consistent way wased in the right way
each and every time so your trading
system should walk you through the
process of analyzing the markets what do
you look at first what next what next
how are you looking at it how are you
defining it how are you making
adjustments all of that kind of stuff um
because then actually when it comes to
the trade decisions well that's just
going to be based on whatever the
expectancy calculation is but this is um
I'm going to go off in a little bit of a
tangent but it's related to this topic
and it's
important and I do want to speed through
the last of this video so I'm not going
to take too long with this but let's say
you have a trade okay we'll do it a
different way this time let's say you've
entered long here because you've done
your calculation and you realize that
there's positive expectancy okay based
on outcomes of this this and up to here
so let's say this plays out now what
action do you take do you exit the trade
well some people do because they have an
order there and like take profit and
they they exit the trade at DMO we use a
context based approach which means that
all of our decisions are based on the
context at that point in time when the
price gets up here the way it's moved up
there the interaction up here various
other factors have adjusted the
probabilities in some way so what we
want to do we want to look at where the
next potential outcomes are maybe it's
down here and up here and estimate the
probabilities of them maybe this one's
too fast we choose one that's a bit
closer up here and we go like okay
that's uh 50% and this is 50% for
example and maybe that's positive
expectancy but not as positive as before
so rather than the amount that we've got
a risk here we want to adjust our risk
we can move our stop loss up here adjust
our Risk by scaling out part of the
trade and leave the rest open maybe it
comes out here and then retests from
this other side and now the
probabilities are so in favor that it's
really positive expectancy and now we
decide to scale in and so on and at some
point we get to a point where it's
negative expectancy okay great exit the
trade because if you play out those
situations over time you're just going
to lose money so all the decisions
become based on the expectancy
calculation
so if you think of it that way what's
the main part of the system is analyzing
the markets in the right way to make
sure that your estimates are going to be
accurate that you're assessing the
potential outcomes in an accurate in a
consistent way and that your probability
estimates are accurate and consistent as
well and then all your decision making
is dictated by that so what else do you
need a system for you don't it's that
part so we can talk about the steps in
your system in another video if you want
to watch that one leave a comment below
also sign up for the free training
because at some point we go through the
the trading system in that or join the D
Trader development program where
literally we cover everything it's over
70 hours of like really detailed content
like I mean I've really gone to town on
like making things evidence-based
covering every aspect of trading that
you need based on my experience helping
hundreds if not thousands of Traders um
from working with someone the best in
the business from researching for years
like I've been obsessed with the markets
now since 2002 that's a really long
[__] time anyway excuse my sales
pitch there then we get on to the final
thing and we'll we'll wrap things up
after this
so if if you've got all of that stuff
covered okay so you know how to estimate
probabilities you know how to do it more
consistently and so on and so on the
only thing that's left is to develop the
skill and to improve your accuracy so
I've combined nine and 10 on here so the
first thing is repetition and feedback
now developing any skill like first of
all we have to accept that estimating
probabilities is a skill and it can be
improved and that's been shown through
research in really complex situations
some more complex than the markets some
people think oh but the markets are more
complex you can't do it for that you can
you could do it for even more complex
situations yes they do
exist so if we accept it's a skill that
needs to be developed to develop any
skill requires
repetition okay so basically in your
brain you have neurons and they have
connections between them and the way
that we develop the skill is we when we
go through repetitions then it creates a
sheath of myelin around the connections
uh between the the neurons and each time
we repeat something it's giving another
layer of myelin this is called the
myelination process and the more myin
there is around a connection the more it
goes from being like dial up internet to
like super fast amazing like futuristic
Broadband whatever the hell I I got
myself way into an area that I don't
know I don't know if broadband's even
the best anymore fiber optic there we go
or I don't know let's leave that there
so you you need reps that's
like it's just a a fundamental thing of
skill development now there are three
broad types of practice you
have ordinary practice you have
purposeful
practice and you have deliberate
practice okay now ordinary
practice if we think about I always give
the same example for this you're
learning to drive you pass you pass your
driving test and then you spend the next
20 years being a cab driver
after 20 years do you think your driving
will be at the level of someone like
leis Hamilton no why because when you're
driving around you're just going through
the EM motions you're not focused you're
paying attention to you know hazards and
things like that and the road signs and
things like that but not the skill of
driving so you go into ordinary practice
and essentially what this means is if we
think about
this it's really badly drawn this is
your comfort zone
got a bit of a lag there this is when
it's too difficult like
it's I didn't write that properly where
it's like you're not going to be able to
achieve the thing and then this like we
call this the
skill challenge Sweet
Spot good luck to anyone who's trying to
read this without hearing me say the
words okay so ordinary practice where
you're driving around for 20 20 years
you're in the comfort zone okay no
progress happening you'll gain some
implicit knowledge and so on implicit
learning but you're not going to be
really def uh developing the skill in
the way that you would if you did
purposeful practice which is where
you're in a skill challenge sweet spot
so you're pushing yourself beyond what
you're capable of not too far that is
too difficult cuz then you're just not
going to do anything you're going to get
learned helplessness and not develop
you're in a skill challenge sweet spot
and you go through repetition and you're
focused on what it is that you're you're
trying to develop at a particular point
in time okay so I'm going to work on
uh taking the right corner line is that
what they do in F1 I think so uh we're
just going to focus on that for a
session in a simulator over and over and
over and over again push myself okay
we're going to go faster speeds and get
the right line and and so on that's
probably not at all what they do but you
get the idea okay so that's the
repetition part so it's it's about being
focused on one area it's about being in
a skill challenge Sweet Spot not your
comfort zone and it's about repetition
makes it purposeful practice and some
other things but you know I'm just
trying to point out the importance of
repetition the thing that makes it then
deliberate practice is a level up from
purposeful practice and this is called
the gold standard of practice it comes
from having a coach that can has been
there and done it and can give you the
right sort of road map to achieve what
you need to achieve and it comes from
getting immediate feedback that you then
uh use to like improve what you're doing
so that's the feedback bit now unless
you're a member in our community or
something you're not going to get
feedback from me on this and like my
guidance my road map but you could if
you want to but instead what you can go
through you can get it yourself like
when we're talking about um the
probability estimates we know that it's
a case of finding where we're less
accurate and improving our accuracy in
those areas so there was this video we
put
out a little while ago so a couple of
videos back that talks you
through this calibration process and
this calibration process you're going to
gain the feedback through this so what
you're essentially doing is is tracking
your probability estimates and then what
I talk you through in this video is a
process of being able to break it down
in different ways to see how accurate
you are so you could break it down by
different elements that you're adjusting
by different setup types different times
of day maybe you're less accurate in the
afternoons in the mornings because
you're just not switched on you can
break it down in any way that you want
to just by following the steps in this
video a lot of people pushed back on the
ideas in that video they said it's not
necessary or it's snake oil or whatever
but essentially it's a process that
takes all of your probability estimates
which you're doing
anyway doing it in a way that you're
measuring it properly getting feedback
on where you're inaccurate or where
you're accurate so you can make the
adjustments and therefore calibrate your
your probability estimates so in some
situations you might be overconfident
some you're underc confident you know
where to adjust so in future when you
encounter that situation you know the
adjustment you need to make so the way
to think about this the way I think
about it is do remember like remote
control
cars under the car so here are the
wheels you have this little
thing here and it's like a little stick
that you can move one side to the other
so when the car is like veering from one
side or the other like when the wheel
axles or whatever the hell is Bend or
something and it's like veering to the
left you can change this so it
recalibrates it so it's slightly to the
right then maybe it's veering too much
to the right so you turn the car over
and do an adjustment until it's more or
less accurate maybe it's difficult to
get it completely straight but you can
more or less over time get it there
that's what I think of with our
caliberation process of our estimates
one the feedback is going to help you
improve your your like ability your your
skill of estimating probabilities um
you'll get more accurate from breaking
things down in a more refined way but
also uh you can look at your accuracy so
if you know like this is perfect
accuracy and you're like this with one
of the elements or something okay from
now on when there's this particular
factor involved in the trade I'm going
to reduce my probability estimate down a
bit and it won't be like this where it's
two straight lines like that if you
watch that video you'll see what I mean
of like the how the chart's going to
look so then you start adjusting down so
when you say okay I'm going to adjust by
5% from now on you do 1% and next time
your line might be here now you need to
adjust up so from now on you go a little
bit higher so it's like 2% and you get
closer and closer and over time it's
closer to being like perfectly accurate
you'll never be
perfect and the thing with the trades is
that we never know with each individual
trade if we were accurate because
there's only one outcome like I said
earlier in the video you can't say it's
60% probability and then it ends up
happening and you say oh [__] I was
wrong so I didn't say 100% it's overtime
you can see on average how accurate you
are you that's the only way to do it so
we're not looking at individual trades
here it's it's the the sort of average
of
so that's why it's not a perfect process
of being exactly accurate it's a
calibration like the car if you're just
making slight adjustments till you
getting closer to being what it looks
like accurate and that's when your
trading becomes more dependable okay so
I just want you to understand here that
you are already estimating probabilities
okay you already doing it if you're
taking trades you are doing it without
realizing it or maybe you are realizing
it and you're just not paying attention
to it whatever but you are doing it you
could at push if someone was challenging
you it and asking you questions Define
the probability you actually think it is
then if you measure that you start to
build evidence of whether you do have an
edge or not now if that is evidence that
you do have an edge fantastic now you're
going to have so much more confidence if
you don't have an edge fantastic now you
know exactly what areas you need to
improve to get yourself to have an edge
either it's going to be through a
calibration process like this it's or
it's going to be breaking down the
probabilities in a better way from
having more accurate base rate is
breaking down the variables better or
you'll realize that the method of
trading you're using is making it
impossible to follow this approach one
it's not allowing you to estimate or to
assess the potential outcomes two it's
not allowing you to break down the
probabilities in any way or like the
aspects in any way and you might realize
that actually it's you're just an
analyzing something meaningless in the
market or it's just too broad-based too
vague it's like this pattern is going to
lead to a 5 to one or just set your stop
loss somewhere around here and you take
profit it's somewhere around here vague
[__] that can't be tested and here's
what happens people will teach you this
rubbish they would never have test it
themselves to see if it actually works
for themselves maybe out of push they've
made some money but when you watch this
video you um you'll see like why that's
not something to rely on but what they
realize is that if it's vague when you
come to them and say I've not been able
to profit from this they'll be able to
say well you need to work on your
trading psychology you need work on your
risk management or you need to practice
identifying the patterns better or some
other nonsense and now from this video
you can hopefully say well no because if
there was an edge and it was objective
then I wouldn't have the trading
psychology problems in most cases and I
would know what's to do with my risk
management and you are just an idiot I
could have said something much worse
then but we'll leave it at that
so you might decide okay I need to
change my trading approach then but at
some point if you've got the right
Trading approach you've gone through and
figured out like what are the potential
issues here and found ways that you need
to break things down better what you're
going to end up with is the ability to
calibrate your trading to improve your
accuracy and over time what you're going
to end up with is to bring It full
circle back to the
beginning this you're going to know you
have an edge and you're going to have
evidence of the edge so you can keep
trading keep trading keep Trading in and
then you have this beautiful situation
that
happens
where you have an
edge
Edge which means that you trade
more which means that you collect more
data which means that you can go through
better
calibration which is going to improve
your Edge which is going to lead you to
trade more collect more data and so on
and so on and this is called a flywheel
effect and I did a video series about
this about this entire thing three
videos including talking about my
trading approach years ago it was when
Co was going on so I've been talking
about this stuff for years but hopefully
now from this video you can see just how
important this is because if you know
you have an edge you've got evidence of
the edge and you can go through this
flywheel effect your trading will just
get better and and better and better so
why rely on luck why rely on vague
things when you can rely on something
that's meaningful
that is dependable and therefore solves
these problems moved more towards the
skill balance no longer lose money on
negative expectancy trades improve your
decision-
making make it easy to improve your
trading through calibration and no
longer have those trading psychology
problems okay so I just wanted to go
back to this slid to have it on screen
as a last reminder while I wrap this up
and I just want to say that if you've
made it this far I really appreciate it
cuz I know from the last video it was
only a small percentage of people that
made it all the way to the end which is
expected it's 2hour video but if you did
make it to the end I want you to leave a
comment something really specific and
I'm going to pick one of the comments
and that person uh if you're up for it
will have a video call to go through
your trading probably spend about half
an hour doing it and discuss how you can
implement this process with your
particular approach to trading or if
you're using the DW method we can just
discuss you know some feedback and stuff
with you there so I want you to leave a
comment and that comment is going to say
we hate Tottenham that's the comment we
hate Tottenham yeah I'm Petty um so
thank you very much for watching also if
you have questions about anything that
we've gone through here leave it down
below in the comment section or watch
through the video again and see if you
pick up the answer for yourself and um
either me someone on my team or one of
our members who have been really helpful
uh can reply to that for you and if
there are other areas you want us to
cover in these sorts of videos let me
know don't forget that free training and
hit the like button and all that sort of
stuff and I'll see you in the next one